We're ready to get underway, and we have further
hearings on the Social Security
Amendment Bill. And the first submitter we have this afternoon is Good Shepherd New
Zealand. We have Good Shepherd New Zealand
online. Bree, over-
Kia ora
Oh, kia ora. Welcome. All right. We have
10 minutes with you this afternoon. The time is yours when you're ready to go.
Thank you, and thank you for the opportunity to speak today.
I'm the policy lead for Good Shepherd New Zealand.
We are a charitable NGO focused on two of the biggest issues facing
women and girls, in particular in New Zealand, being poverty and family violence,
and the challenges that stem from these.
First, I'll speak to the policy tightening eligibility criteria for jobseeker
support. So as noted in MSD's own RIS, the
benefits for young people of these changes are likely to be significantly
outweighed by the costs, and we're really concerned about the further hardship that
this may create for households. We do understand the need to target funding
towards those who most need it. But as the cost of living has risen, New
Zealand has seen more poverty and more of the squeezed middle, lower to
middle-income households who are struggling to make ends meet.
There is a serious risk that many families will not be able to financially support
their children past their school years.
As New Zealand is already experiencing high and unmoving child poverty rates
due to the financial pressures on households with children, these households are
also facing rising energy costs and food prices increasing, amongst
other things. Stagnant incomes at the moment are not sufficient
to meet these costs.
The Helen Clark Foundation's recent report on social cohesion found that one
in four New Zealand households go without meals because they can't afford food,
and the clients that we serve report similar activity.
The parental income limit in this policy, which is around $65,000 to
$67,000, is much lower than the annual gross
household income, which is currently sitting at around $139,000, and also
lower than some other parental income tests that we see for payments, such as the
student allowance, which is around $101,000 if you live with your
parents. It's currently unclear how family size and other dependents will be
taken into consideration here. What is clear is that young people
whose parents earn over this threshold but who will not or cannot support
them will be left behind. Rainbow youth and those experiencing family violence will
likely be over-represented in this group, especially where estrangement is
difficult to prove.
We note that the first two objectives in this policy, as noted in the bill, center
on fiscal sustainability and incentivizing youth to enter work.
But making it harder for young people to access the jobseeker benefit will not
incentivize them to enter a job market if there are no jobs to hire them.
The recent 2026 Salvation Army State of the Nation report states that over a
quarter of a million people are currently wanting work but are unable to find
it. That challenge is very real. The entry-level job market in
particular is challenged due to the rise of AI, the global economic
context, and many young people are applying for hundreds of jobs without
success. Under this policy, young people will also miss out on some of the
coaching and support that are offered by case managers through the jobseeker
benefit that might really be able to help them when applying for those roles.
We think that government policy should focus on investing in labor market
stimulus, increasing business activity, opportunities, and
education. MSD's original preferred option was
to provide a range of targeted employment and changing programs which predicted
savings in the long term through lower future benefit
levels. We do know that Budget 2026 has promised an
extra thousand Youth Guarantee places, which is great.
But given the policy in this bill is estimated to impact over
4,000 young people, there is a significant gap here.
We also know that unfortunately, many of the young people who are currently
struggling to find work are university graduates already, showing that
education alone is not currently sufficient to pull youth out of
unemployment. The job market needs to be stimulated as well to provide new
opportunities for those who are exiting tertiary education.
People also need funds to enable employment opportunities.
Young people who are denied benefits and have no money to buy a car
cannot travel to a job if public transport options don't exist.
They can't afford appropriate work wear for a job interview or buy tools needed for
their trade. They cannot pay for that additional training that could support them
into work. While the majority of the loans that we provide, so no
interest, no fee loans for people under a certain income threshold, they're usually
for things like a car or debt consolidation, we do also provide loans for
educational or training-related expenses or technology like laptops to
enable study. There is a need for these things.
If parents are forced to become financially responsible for their children for
longer, it's also likely that there'll be an increase in demand for assistance
provided by NGOs or charities like ourselves or food banks.
For example, the Zero Hunger Collective here at Kaikoore reports an increase in
two-income households who are visiting food banks across the country.
This is expected to only worsen. So that's in work poverty in
action. Charities and social services fill a really
needed gap in responses to poverty, but many have been forced to
close down due to funding cuts or contracts not being renewed.
The charitable sector can't be the ambulance at the bottom of the cliff, and we're
not going to succeed if there aren't contracts to fund them to do so.
I'll now move on to the second proposal in the Bill, changing the entry threshold
for the accommodation supplement.
We note that housing makes up a significant portion of financial
pressure for many households. Housing tends to be a fixed household
cost, so that's unable to be reduced or budgeted around.
While the majority of our clients are in rental or some form of
social housing, around 13% live in a home that they own
themselves. So this shows that despite owning their house, these
clients are under enough financial pressure to need to come to us to be able
to purchase those essential goods and services such as whiteware, for
example. Now, there is a number of reasons why people who own
homes may be experiencing financial stress.
Even though we have seen some house price trend improvement and some shifts
in the affordability criteria, which is fantastic, those who
bought homes at record highs or are locked in those higher interest
rates will continue to struggle.
Local government rates across the country are also set to increase 5% to
10% in the coming year. High numbers of redundancies
across all sectors, public, private, and social sector,
seriously reduce household incomes, especially in this really tough
job market we're currently in, where unemployment might be extended.
Divorce or separation can result in one person taking over a mortgage
unexpectedly, and this is particularly challenging when family violence is
involved. Both situations disproportionately impact women's
financial wellbeing. Simply stating that the accommodation supplement
exists to help homeowners accumulate a personal asset
ignores the current state of the economy and the variable housing market.
I'll share a quick example of a Good Shepherd client who I'll call Lillian.
Lillian had experienced family violence in her relationship with her ex-husband.
When he left, she suddenly found herself to be a solo mum living in the
house that they legally co-owned together, but he'd stopped paying the mortgage,
maintenance for the house, any other bills.
The washing machine broke, the shower leaked, but she couldn't afford to fix them.
While trying to get her life back together after abuse, she had to navigate paying
these bills alone on a limited budget.
With our help, she was eventually supported into financial stability, but this
example shows some of the complexity of homeowner situations and how
it's often a lot more complicated than that.
So if this Bill goes through, we do really strongly support
the exclusions that are noted, especially for superannuants.
Our own research into single older women's housing needs has shown
that many older people who own their home do not experience
affordable, warm housing. Poor housing quality, particularly
for older homes that were purchased potentially many decades ago,
combined with rising rates and insurance costs, put significant pressure on
superannuant homeowners who lack the ability to generate additional
income. Just another client example I'll share.
We have recently supported an 80-year-old woman living in rural
South Island, so the deep south. Her house was purchased
many decades ago, and she couldn't afford to upkeep it.
Her health was really suffering because the heating was completely inadequate
during the freezing winters. Her family lived far away, and she was
reliant completely on the super. Her budget was really tight, and she couldn't
afford to buy a heat pump. So we were able to support her by providing a grant, and
we've helped many others like her with this kind of essential home maintenance
needs. But this shows how older people are desperately in need of any
dollar that they are able to get, especially because they can't
earn the additional income.
So overall, we are disappointed to see another policy progressing that's
focused on these short-term financial savings instead of long-term
outcomes. We believe that kicking the can down the road does not
support financial sustainability in the long run.
It just creates false economies, and we need to take a long-term
lens. Thank you for your time.
Thank you. Any questions, members?
Francesca.
Thank you, and a very comprehensive submission from Good Shepherd.
I'm interested in what you said earlier about
the struggle for young people to find work and employment opportunities.
Can you elaborate on what you're seeing on the ground?
Yeah. Partly it's hard because we're a small service, so unfortunately,
we can't support everybody. What we see a lot of the time is people who come to us
who don't meet affordability criteria, and that's
the hardest thing, is having to turn people away because legally, we can't put
people into further hardship. But, yeah, we're seeing a lot
of people doing it tough at the moment, and I think it's going to get harder if the
job market, in particular, doesn't improve.
Thank you.
All right. Thank you for coming and making a submission this afternoon.
Thank you for the written submission as well.
Kia ora. Thank you.
All right. Our next submitter is
the
Manuel Poe Family Whānau Trust.
Hello again, Frances.
Now, I see you've-
From-
... basically put the same submission as I had the committee yesterday on a
different bill. I'll just make a couple of quick comments before you get underway.
Section 25 of the Crimes Act,
I've been a lawyer and worked in the courts all across New Zealand.
That is regards to crimes. The government
establishes the law, so that's not relevant to this
committee's consideration of this bill.
And, the New Zealand government is not registered
under the foreign government of the US Securities and Exchanges Commission, so
that's not relevant either. But look, if you-
The New Zealand government isn't-
Correct. But if you want to make submissions that are relevant-
Under the US securities
... if you want to make submissions that are relevant to this bill, I'm happy to
hear that, but I would ask you to make submissions that are relevant to the bill
that we're considering.
So you aren't ignorant to the law then?
No, we make the law. So we're interested in hearing your submissions on the-
So you do know about the law, right?
On the bill that we're considering.
Okay. All right. So,
kia ora koutou.
This is a demand on request under urgency, a
notification of a cease and desist under the official
complaints, and a demand on request, a independent internal
investigation into the Social Security bill.
This is against the Coalition Government Select Committee, House of
Representatives,
and the Governor General,
identifying any unusual legislative features of this
bill. This bill is flawed.
We do not give consent to any ADM or Social
Security bill at this time. It fails to comply with the treaty
principles. It fails to comply to the Privacy Act
2020. It fails to comply to the New Zealand Bill of Rights
Act. Failing to comply to the Public Service Act
2020. Request for all private and
financial information concerning the Social Security bill.
Certification and accreditation process to give a provided the
safeguard for any use of ADM.
Does these safeguards have unintended
bias, or
discrimination
against Māori
or other groups, cultures, or other forms of
disabilities?
Is it in compliance with the principles of the treaty,
and does it follow the Bill of Rights Act?
Note that one of the requirements under the ADM standards is that
where unintended bias cannot be removed or significantly
mitigated from a ADM process,
human involvement must be in process at all
times, or decisions will be made by
human involvement, which would then mean that the
decision is no longer an automated decision.
Automated decision-
Sorry, Frances. Can I just pause you there for a moment?
This bill is not considering automated decision-making.
This bill-
So it's not in there?
I think you're thinking of a separate bill.
There was one, but-
There was one previously, but that's not this one.
It's not this one?
No, correct.
Okay. Does the department have a disclosure statement?
Has the MSD prepared a disclosure statement concerning any
access information to the scrutiny of this bill?
Does this bill consist with the principles of the
Treaty of Waitangi?
Has the government engaged with Māori?
Has the government consulted with Māori?
Under the privacy and standards of the New Zealand Bill of Rights, has the
government complied to the rules, regulations, legislations, under their
responsibilities, obligations, and duties?
Under the coalition government, within three years, the government has put New
Zealand citizens and Māori into a financial economic crisis,
bringing harm to the most vulnerable.
We have the highest rates of unemployment, homelessness, crime,
incarceration, business liquidations, mortgagee sales,
rises in cost of living, food, gas, water, rent, medical
cost, and power. Shortage of disability services, public
services, government-funded services.
Nurses, doctors, not enough funding.
Teachers, police, fire, ambulance, not enough funding.
How has the government made provisions for our most
vulnerable?
The government,
with this bill, along with other bills
they have submitted and created to
harm public,
has caused public scrutiny
and unrest due to the intentional, deliberate action of
the coalition benefiting from the corporation as a corporate
entity.
No, it-
Bringing harm and poverty and financial economic crisis,
attacking our most vulnerable through these bills.
A demand and request for all official financial private information
concerning the
Social Security bill.
Why is this bill
targeting our most vulnerable?
How have they made-
Provisions for our most vulnerable.
Does the government have any plans
of stopping the financial economic
crisis that we are facing today as New
Zealand citizens and
Māori? The Manuel Pou Family
Whānau Trust demand on request under urgency an official complaint, a
notification of a cease and desist, an independent internal
investigation, and official information into this
bill
for the suppression, oppression, persecution against the most
vulnerable
Māori,
the disabled,
the poor
of New Zealand.
And we wish you,
government and select committee, to answer these questions, please.
Thank you.
All right. Thank you, Frances. Any questions for Frances Manners?
No, thank you.
Yeah.
Willie.
Frances, just explain to us
about the treaty principles. How do you see the treaty principles being
breached?
So with the treaty principles, when it comes to Māori,
we have self-management rights to
control our own resources and our own affairs.
Also, under Kāwanatanga, we recognize
under Crown that the
government
is to make laws for the country, which is fair and just.
We all must be treated equally,
ensure that all New Zealand citizens are equal before the
law,
and we must have reasonable cooperation, requires
both parties to act in good faith and engage in
fair consultation. And also, we
must have the right to redress, impose
any obligations
on the Crown to provide process of resolving any
grievances and past breaches to our treaty
partnership.
Kia ora, Frances. Thanks for making a submission this afternoon.
Make a lot of sense to me, Frances.
Thank you very much.
All right.
Ka pai.
Getting my questions off
I don't think you had any more questions.
Ka pai. Thank you, Frances. Well done. Keep it up.
So you
buy the argument, do you, Willie?
I really agree with that we're all equal before the law.
I agree with that. Agree we're all equal, absolutely.
We're all equal before the law.
All right. Now, next submitter is a Māori woman-
And Māori have special set of rights, as you well know
... Māori Women's Welfare League.
Oh, ask me that question as well, will you?
Do it just for New Zealand first.
All right. Well, welcome. We have 10 minutes with you this afternoon. Welcome.
Kia ora.
Kia ora. My name is Hope Tupara, and I'm the national president of the Māori
Women's Welfare League. Thank you for-- You've read my
written submission, ka pai.
This bill is dumb.
And it's dumb because
it isn't going to save money.
It's going to cause more costs down the track.
Most of our kids get on okay.
Even kids that are studying now or working, they're still struggling.
We've got lots of young ones struggling.
So
we reject this bill, and we think you should reject it as well.
Because you're targeting vulnerable young
people who are struggling
more than their peers.
Can't get jobs.
Typically,
Māori kids leave school a bit earlier than their
peers.
We also know that Māori women tend to have babies younger,
so they're going to end up-- And we have a lot of single Māori women
looking after their children. So that means they're going to have teenagers a
lot sooner than some of their other women.
And we've got a lot of generations living in one house, not just
Māori either. A lot of Pākehas are living with lots of
generations in their house to cope because of homelessness, because
they don't want to be homeless.
I was just talking to one the other day, a Pākeha woman who's got
young people, lots of generations living in her house because that's
how they're trying to cope.
Now, when you've got lots of generations, it causes a lot of stress, as you
probably know. If you've got children, grandparents.
Because our homes now are not designed like marae
for lots of people living under one roof.
So you're going to naturally have a lot of stress.
Now, most of the people in this room have benefited from past
policies of government, where there were lots of jobs.
You could go from one job to another.
There was a lot of money in education, and so
I benefited from that in tertiary.
A lot of us did.
But we are imposing on young people a set of conditions today
that none of us, well, a lot of us in this room, didn't have to go
through. But they are going through. But I ask you, why?
Why are we targeting our young people?
Why are we doing this to them? They are going to be the workforce of the future.
And we've taken away student loans.
We put more penalizing young people.
We've done lots of things to young people, and I don't get it.
I don't understand why we're doing that to young people when many of us
have not had those conditions in which we grew up and
went into work. So I ask you,
for a lot of reasons, that a lot of the submitters have already talked about.
You're not going to save money. It's going to hit you down the track.
You're impacting people who are already vulnerable.
You're impacting people who are actually doing okay, but
just surviving.
Young people, it's a special thing to want to have
independence.
We've all been there. You know what it feels like when you've had enough of living
under somebody's roof with somebody else's rules, and you need your own space.
And I'm not talking about
people who
have got no choice. I'm talking about people who actually got a choice,
but actually you're limiting some of the choices for many of our young people.
So you need to throw this bill out. And like she said,
it's a breach of Te Tiriti o Waitangi.
And the reason it's a breach is because I want to know how many people, how
many of you have actually gone into the communities and sought
solutions in partnership with our hapū and iwi.
Because I know that it's affecting mostly Māori.
This bill is going to affect mostly Māori youth.
And if you want to work in partnership, you want to work under Te Tiriti, then go
and see the people on the ground and ask them for the solutions.
That's where they are.
Not in this whare. Anyway, that's me.
I've had enough. Sorry.
Thank you. I want to just make a couple of comments and then a sort of question.
Yes.
Because I'm not one of those who benefited. I'm a kid.
No, a bit later.
I'm a kid-
Yes
... in the '80s and '90s who-
True
... especially the '80s, had no food on the table.
And had to work really hard to get out of poverty.
And
also, didn't get anything
free. The university, I had to pay for all that.
Well, not didn't have to pay for it because the government actually pays 85%
roughly of university.
And none of these kids now actually want to be on the benefit.
Yeah, and that's coming to my question.
Because this is targeting 18 to 19-year-olds who are sort of in that really
important transition between family, the family home,
school, often, and the rest of their
lives. And so this is a
really important, I think you want to hear a few things, a really important part of
their lives, and we want to encourage them to either employment or
education or training. Because it is-
That doesn't exist, and you know it.
You know that the NEET rates have gone
up, and you know that unemployment's gone up in the last quarter.
So the conditions that you're talking about don't actually exist like they used
to. Even in your time, they were better than they are now.
They were.
I'm not sure about that, to be fair, but the-
No, I'm sure about it.
Would you agree that it'd be better
for young people to be in training
or study if they're not in employment, to ultimately upskill and
to help get them ready for employment?
I don't think it's available everywhere, though.
Even though you have training programs around
the country, it's not necessarily available
everywhere.
And
in the rural areas, sometimes it's actually harder because you don't have access to
public transport like you might do in the cities.
I don't know if it's easier in the cities, to be honest.
But in many families,
they might have just the one car. It's a bit harder now with petrol
costs.
And so you're kind of reliant on somebody taking
you in their car or public transport to get to training.
Mm.
So, I mean, other submitters have probably
canvassed a lot of the issues that come up.
But in rural areas, so I live in a kind of a rural
area.
Mm.
But we have very limited public transport.
There are some training centers in the area, but they usually
are quite specific courses.
Yeah. I grew up in a rural area.
Yeah.
And still live in one now. Willie.
Can I just ask,
with the Māori Women's Welfare,
this is a kaupapa being traversed amongst all our women, is it?
This-
Yeah. Well, because our branches, we've got
160 branches across the country.
Yeah.
And they're on the ground.
Mm.
So, they've got firsthand contact with a lot of our young people
anyway. Apart from their own, there's other young people
that are
in the community.
Yeah.
And they're not necessarily just Māori either.
No.
Because they might be their friends, too.
I know. And also, yes and no. I mean, you guys were having some love affair with
Winston there for a while. And so he can,
just for David's information, he might not know that he-
Know all about that, my friend.
And so
him and Shane, they'd be backing you on this, wouldn't they?
Well, I would like to hope so.
Yeah. I would've thought that was-
Are you New Zealand First?
Oh, yes.
Oh, yes. Are you?
We love your work.
Yeah, they love your work.
Do you love what I just said?
No, probably not.
Parts of it.
Okay.
But I would say that I've worked with your mate Honi up north, as an
example.
And on the ground looking at ways to create employment and
usually with hapū and with
iwi. To me, that's kind of a way forward, but it's not
asking you a question because that's my job.
I'm meant to be asking you a
question.
I see the question was-
Helen. Helen.
No. You said that we were going to
pay for this later And so I'd like to know about that.
My second question, so you can choose really, because we haven't got much time,
but is what about the pressure on those parents that you were talking
about. Those parents, we need more kids in this country.
Yeah.
We're about to load on parents of
18-year-olds a whole bunch more-
Mm
... financial pressure.
Exactly. What was your first question?
The first question, what are the consequences that you spoke of?
Oh. Well, just imagine. Mental health problems comes
to mind straight away.
Mm.
Because it's a stressful time being a teenager.
There's a lot of hormones going on.
There's a lot of stress, a lot of pressure.
Your parents want you to do this, they want you to do that.
Your peers want you to do this, they want you to do that.
But also you internally want things for yourself as well.
And if you can't get them, that
would be psychologically damaging.
Mm.
And then that would lead to all sorts of physical
ailments. So health is the immediate one that comes to
mind.
And then, if you get into desperation,
you might go down a bad track, maybe even commit
crime because you've got no other choice.
Oh.
So that's another pipeline, isn't it?
It's a potential pipeline.
A job is good.
A job is good if you get a job.
Yeah.
You need somebody who actually will employ you.
And these days, it's usually someone that knows you.
If you're a young Maori kid, you're probably less likely to be employed.
That's a fact.
Oh, thank you, Dr. Hope. Appreciate you coming in and making a submission.
Thank you.
And thank you for leaving us time for questions as well. I really appreciate it.
No
worries.
Thank you.
The next submitter is, Parents of Vision Impaired NZ via Zoom.
Good evening, Dr. Rebecca. Welcome.
Kia ora. Lovely to be here.
Nice to see you all again.
Likewise. All right. The time is yours when you're ready.
Lovely. So I'm here on behalf of Parents of Vision
Impaired New Zealand.
PVI supports the goal of enabling young people to participate in
education, employment, and community life.
However, we are concerned that this bill moves in the opposite direction for our
disabled young people by increasing barriers to income
support without addressing the barriers that
prevent their participation in the first place.
I didn't cover in my written submission about why a disabled
young person might receive job seeker support, either job
seeker support or job seeker health and disability rather than supported living
payment. And I just wanted to cover that
briefly, because our parents tell us that the SLP is
extremely difficult to obtain for the young person.
It requires extensive administration work and a raft of
documentation. And the SLP does have a carve-out for totally
blind persons, but not all of our vision-impaired young
persons are totally blind.
So that creates a challenge. What it means is that sometimes
disabled young people receive job seeker because they do not meet
the current eligibility criteria for
supported living. It has a higher threshold based on the impact of
disability on a person's ability to work or sustain employment.
Young people may also have some potential work capacity,
even though meaningful employment can be difficult to access without
significant support.
Also, transitioning from school is
complex. While its supports may exist on
paper, we call these supports as imagined,
rather than supports as they exist.
Our parents talk about the transition cliff after school.
They talk about transitioning to what.
There's very little for our young persons to transition
into, particularly as it relates to vision-related
disabilities, because they impact so much on young people's ability to
engage in education, their employment prospects, daily living,
and ability to navigate the labor market.
As I mentioned, barriers to employment include inaccessible
workplaces, lack of transport options, employer attitudes,
the need for workplace accommodations, limited availability of
specialist employment support, and disrupted education pathways.
Job seeker can act as a stabilizing support
during this transition period while a young person recovers from
schooling. And I'd note there that vision does create an
extra challenge and does exhaust our young people sometimes.
So sometimes they need a bit of time to recover as they prepare to seek
further employment and training.
This gives them time to explore rehabilitation options, disability-related
supports, and explore part-time study options.
And this is where the other stuff gets interesting, because part-time
study isn't as well-supported as full-time study,
and it can be really difficult to navigate this
financially. And so our concern is that this bill creates
barriers to financial support without addressing the underlying
challenges, and instead increases financial hardship and
makes it harder to achieve independence.
The bill does assume that family support is available.
But as I'm sure you're aware from the stats around disability,
households with a disabled person, including a disabled child, have
consistently higher rates of material hardship than households
without.
Families with a disabled child are more likely to experience material
deprivation, more likely to experience financial stress,
more likely to report unmet health and disability-related needs,
and disability in childhood is associated with higher household
costs, reduced parental employment, and a higher likelihood of
living in an income-poor household.
This means that these households are less able to provide financial
support when a child turns 18.
For our young people, turning 18 does not necessarily represent the
transition into independence in the way this policy
assumes. Instead, it's actually a transition
period where they need more support.
More support to navigate the options, more support to navigate
employment or further education, more support to understand
disability services and adult systems.
For our young people, income support is the foundation that allows them to
participate.
It helps with things like the additional cost of transport, which is
increasing due to the cuts to total mobility.
It helps with the support and assistive technology.
As some of you would have heard during the submissions on the DSS bill, some of
these costs are not adequately covered by DSS.
If they want to undertake volunteer work or to
explore that kind of volunteer options in terms of what could
work, that comes with costs.
So reducing access to income support before employment barriers are addressed
makes the pathway into employment harder, not
easier. And lastly, we're also concerned about the
proposed changes around the accommodation supplement,
and that is because
of those income-related challenges, and it's really important,
particularly when you have a disabled child, that you have stability and
accessibility and continuity of care.
And so that accommodation support can help those households to
retain that stability. And I'm going to stop
there because that gives you time.
Oh, we recommend rejection of the bill and
removing or revising parental income testing,
particularly as it relates to a disabled child.
We'd also like to see disability impact analysis done
in regard to welfare reforms prior to coming to select
committee. So yeah, time for questions.
All right. Thanks, Rebecca.
Questions, members?
David.
Thank you very much, Rebecca.
I've worked with a lovely lady called Minnie Barr-Guinath for a number
of years. She's on the board.
And you'll know her well. One of the issues that we
confronted quite regularly was that there's a lack of
understanding in the workplace about what people
with vision impairments can offer and how easy it is.
Is that a real pinch point for your organization and the people that you
serve?
Yeah. Yeah, it is. It's hard because our young people
don't... I don't want to say they don't know how to advocate. They do.
But some of that is learning that occurs over time.
So adults often have had a bit more experience in that, whereas an
18-year-old's still navigating the world as a newly minted
adult and trying to figure this stuff out.
And the barriers they face, you're young,
and you have a vision impairment, and you may not know what
supports are available or how to access the supports.
And some of those supports exist on paper, but if, A, if you're not aware of them,
but B, if you don't know how to access them, they might as
well not exist. So that's a real challenge, too, is trying to
keep our young people informed as to what supports exist
out there and how they can go about navigating that space.
So Rebecca, I'm actually asking about the employer side.
Oh, sorry.
Yeah. So,
they just don't know how or what they're dealing with and-
Yeah
... aware.
Yeah.
Yeah. And I can understand, too, employers, they want
someone who can do the job, and they're often really reluctant because they don't
know if this person can do the job and
they're there, they've got a particular goal in mind, and they're not a social
service. And there's a real tension there around how do we
support employers because they don't know how to...
They're quite-- I don't think they mean to be discriminatory, but they're often
quite discriminatory.
Not all.
Then I've got a-- It's almost like a sub my question.
Sure.
We've heard a lot about people who, they
don't want to go into
more study. They want to work, and they apply and apply and
apply, and they can't get it. And we've heard people say that often the
only way they get a job is because they've got a friend or
there's a contact. Do you see that when it comes
to young people with disabilities, that-
Oh-
... they get the jobs through friends?
Absolutely. Absolutely. There's a young man,
I won't share the name because obviously we're here.
But he's phenomenal. He's incredibly capable.
Totally blind, uses braille. A
very, very competent young man. Can't get work.
The only work he get-- Even with the supports
that are available, they offered him very menial labor, even though he's a very
capable, competent, intelligent young man.
They saw his disability and automatically sort of sent him into
very menial
work, and he's like, "Well, actually, I do want to go to university.
I'm just not ready straight after school, and I want to work in a field that's
related to what I want to study and what I'm interested in." And yet he couldn't
even get
that sort of volunteer intern unpaid type situation because
of the nature of his disability. It's heartbreaking.
Yeah, thanks
And frustrating because it's-
Yeah
... untapped potential.
Yeah.
That's all right. All right, thank you very much, Rebecca, for coming and making
the submission this afternoon.
Thank you very much.
And thanks for Riddles' submission as well.
Our next minute
is-
Just apologies, you go to minister.
Okay, all right.
They added an issue since I've got that seat down.
Oh, okay. All right.
And we are still unable to raise that beneficiary to progress, so you
might need to break for it.
Okay. All right. Well, let's-
Suspend
... suspend while we find some more submitters.
How long for?
Not sure.
We could go to, I don't know,
we could go 10 or 15 minutes.
Yeah.
And some more.
Yeah?
Yeah. All right.
15 minutes, if that's okay.
Let's wait 15 minutes.
Okay, see you at quarter to.
All right.
Thank you.
Excellent
Sorry.
All right. Good afternoon. Welcome. Max, is it?
G'day.
Yeah, g'day.
Hi.
All right. Welcome. Thanks for coming in.
We've got you for 1:00 this afternoon, so
fire away.
All right, good stuff.
Good afternoon,
chair and members of the panel. Thank you
for the opportunity to speak to you today.
I have a number of concerns about the bill.
This bill would affect the most vulnerable group in our society
at a most vulnerable stage of life.
It might be good if I begin to talk to you about my ongoing
correspondence with
Louise Upston. I have asked the honorable
minister what does she think is the purpose of paid work.
She has, however, stated that she wants families to have better
opportunities, choices, and support.
But is unclear on what form or source these will come from.
The broadcaster Ian Fraser
saw New Zealand as a very peculiar society.
He thought that we,
as a nation, believed that we could get the best out of people by
giving them very little.
I do believe there are successes in society, but people who
have done well for themselves. But for many people, it has been in
spite of these difficulties, not be because of them.
And I want to remove as many hurdles as possible for people to
succeed.
We can agree that a family living together in cramped conditions whose
source of income is from the state is not a good
thing.
Where we differ may be in terms of the remedy, if that is a
goal,
of seeing how they will become self-supporting,
declining outside contributions.
If anything, the work I have done as an advocate
informs me working with individuals
to see change, not just in financial terms, but also in their life, is
hard and very unrewarding in terms of progress,
as their situation has often been the result of families
washing their hands of them or their own bad
decisions and actions.
In that looking at the problem as a simple formula on a balance
sheet is a very reductionist way which allows for no accommodation of
the changes which have occurred in society.
And I've asked the minister,
what does she think is the purpose of paid work?
And I'm not sure what we should
be able to feel we should expect from our politicians, but
my expectation of a minister would be that she might offer some
critique of perspective and thought.
In considering her position, one might think that she's best
placed to answer such a question.
Authors such as Anne Else and
others have attempted to answer the question,
but how then does it relate to the bill?
The law change does not answer this question, nor how a person might be able
to manage financially. It simply does what it states it is going
to do.
If I look back 50 years
at
society, if a person was still at
home at 16, people would ask why hadn't they left
home already.
The society and the economic conditions today is different from then.
Social policy has at least stated that
families are the first port of call.
However, this is very different to the reality of the
family.
Families
have not been predictable sources in terms of support.
There has been little forethought by this government to this bill
as there has been to my question from the minister, and I'd ask you
to remove the bill.
Thank you.
Thanks, Max. What do you think is the purpose of paid work?
I think it is part of
a formula, part of how
income
comes into
a household.
I think
traditionally we've arranged our lives,
the prevalent model in society has been
households headed up by
a heterosexual couple And if a herb can be brought to
life, and obviously the
money plays
a role in that.
And
I'd
want to see,
I think there needs to be more depth in how we look at
that issue. And
policies like this
are really a continuation of an
unfinished business. We haven't
decided collectively
how we
manage these things.
I was thinking about my
father. My father grew up on dairy farm in the
'50s and '60s. And when he was 16,
most of the boys on
the road, they
left at 16 and they were working for their
fathers on the farm.
People's
situation today is so much
different. And I can think of one person who's
a friend of mine who lives at home,
on a domestic purpose benefit, and
whenever
a child with autism hit her, was a king
hit. And
I think it came down to money. She had a carer support.
And we're looking at something like
$100.
It's not a
hill that you're going to pick a battle on to die.
But I think there is
a need for thinking much deeply.
At the moment, social policy is very much
orientated inside of economic
policy. I don't like it. I'd like that to change.
And I see the project which we had-
Sorry. We'll have to just finish it up.
But no, thank you very much for making submission this afternoon. Thanks.
Thank you very much.
Thank you.
Our next submitter is
Sam Gleisner.
Sam Summers.
Sam Summers. Sam Summers, okay.
Sorry. I thought Summers.
Welcome.
So yeah, I've got five minutes with you this afternoon.
You are welcome and
okay.
Thanks.
Yeah. Sorry, get your name again.
Sam Gleisner.
Sam Gleisner. Excellent. All right, great. Cheers.
Tena koutou katoa. Sam Gleisner,
taku ingoa.
I'm very grateful to be here today, and thank you for your time for listening to my
submission. I'm going to give a short personal response to this bill.
Last week, I was listening to
Bishop Justin Duckworth speak at the Wellington City Mission,
and he talked primarily about the need for care in
our communities. I think if other
people were
in the same kind of work or volunteering
in the same organizations, supporting people
who are in need, I think they would agree with him.
I'm sure they'd all not support this bill,
because they would understand that this bill, over
time, creates more people who need that care and support.
I understand that this bill will create approximately 35
million in savings over the coming four years.
And that those savings are intended to be redirected to more efficient
social sector initiatives.
I think this is a good thing.
But I think it's really important to think about the context
that that's in.
Because in the last year,
as you probably know, 150 of the wealthiest
individuals and families increased their wealth by
approximately $26 billion. So that was in one year,
an increase to their wealth of $26 billion.
We're told
regularly that
these people are necessary and needed in New Zealand, that
they
contribute to the economy through investments, and that we need the jobs that are
created,
that we
need
the spending that they contribute to the economy, and they need
also to not be incentivized to take that
wealth offshore.
Personally, I call b******t to that.
I call b******t that the people that are affected by this bill deserve
to have the lives of themselves and their whanau
made that much harder,
and that the families of those 150
individuals deserve
that wealth increase over one year.
So to me,
this bill just demonstrates that the parties
currently in government
are entirely equitable.
And that they're entirely equitable
in that when it comes to some New Zealanders,
they're equitable about how little they care.
Tena koutou, tena koutou, tena koutou katoa.
Thanks. I just have a question because the
explanation of this bill is that the change is to
reinforce the expectation that young people, 18 and 19-year-olds, who are
not in employment,
training, or education. So those three, employment, education, or training,
will be supported by their parents above a certain threshold.
It's the same threshold for everyone,
as opposed to being on a welfare beneficiary.
Now, in the context that the advice that government's been given is that young
people who go on welfare,
for quite a short period of time on average end up being, or
expected to be on it for up to 21 years in their lifetime.
Is it a good outcome for young people to be expected to spend 21
years of their lifetime on a beneficiary, or would it be better for them to
have education,
training, or employment that can give them further opportunities?
Personally, I think
that
it would be beneficial. I'm not sure if I mentioned
it in my written submission, but I think
the vast, vast majority of
New Zealanders want to contribute meaningfully to New Zealand's economy and
society. And,
although it's very hard to
know this
sort of fully,
I am around children quite a lot and,
a small number, but
I see their kind of hope and aspirations and
willingness to contribute. So I don't accept
that
it's choices or
that those individuals who are unable or find it difficult to work or
contribute, do it out of their own...
It's their fault, essentially.
And in the same way, I think the
wealthiest people that I talked about,
many would disagree, but it's not their agency primarily
that
I think... The notion that they work
a thousand or 10,000 times harder than others
is
ridiculous. So yeah.
Well, thanks Sam for coming in and making submissions this afternoon.
Cool. Thank you. Thank you all.
Our next submitter is Sam Summers online.
Looks like I've made it.
No, good day, Sam.
Good afternoon.
Welcome. We can see and hear you-
Thank you
... so fire away when you're ready.
Okay. I personally oppose
this bill here on the basis I have
personally
been kicked out of home at 18
and
basically have had everything withheld from me with a 10-foot
barge post from my mother.
I can see other people
in my similar circumstances,
be told that they would
be
not helped
under this current bill. What helped me was the fact that I had the unemployment
benefit that was able to sit there and keep me financially going till I
got myself back on track.
In my early 20s, based on the broken down situation, I tried
studying. I'll tell you this right now,
StudyLink, independent circumstances was a complete joke
to go through. It did not take into effect my broken down
situation. I took a complaint to my local MP, then Nathan Guy.
I got a telling off from his
electoral secretary for not sucking it up,
and ended up, as a result, falling back on the unemployment benefit
because I could not get,
was it, StudyLink. And that's also pushed me off looking for tertiary
education. I have known other people of the members of the
LGBTQ community who have been kicked out because of their sexuality,
and they would be told, "Oh, but if you stop being gay or stop being trans, you can
come home." And the Work and Income case manager, the way this
legislation is rubber-stamped, will sit there and go, "Oh well, you can
go home as long as you stop being trans and stop being yourself and put a mask on"
to sit there and do this. It also sits there and traps people in domestic violence
situations of it, which could end up having someone being healed abuse
potentially for an extra two years.
The legislation itself,
even though it has exemptions there, I'll be honest with you, the exemptions are
just as restrictive as the United States total abortion ban
exemptions, with the exception of rape, but only when the
rapist is convicted. Based on that one, if that
scenario is put into place, the child will be two years old.
Now, this legislation, by the time
all the steps would be done, that person would sit down there and get the
support, it will be possibly by their 21st
birthday.
This bill needs to really look at and also put in
places
the wording of
the last
resort to
get Social Security assistance is the part that will lead to
people who should be accepted be wrongly declined.
Now, I've personally have dealt with Work and Income in the past.
This is sad that we live in a society where I have to often threaten,
"Oh, well, you made a bad decision. You haven't explained it good to me.
How about I file an injunction in the High Court, and you can
explain what you're withholding from me to a High Court judge?
And if you can't be bothered explaining it to a High Court judge, be prepared to
hold in contempt." That is the current society we live in when dealing with MSD.
These young 18, 19-year-olds won't have the opportunity to even
sit down there and realize that that's an option or a threat on the table to
make Win, Work and Income, who consistently
make bad decisions contrary to law into it.
It is also known that something about 70%
of review of decisions are overturned
in the favor of the beneficiary. So in turn,
you ask questions, how much are they making? This is already happening.
When people question things, it's already been overturned.
People who should be on Supported Living Payment benefit,
currently if you apply, you may be put on job seekers with medical deferral
until they assess it. If you're 18 or 19 years old,
and your parents earn too much, you may not even get into the queue to
be assessed for Supported Living Payment until you turn 20
years old. Because instead of your
application going forward to Supported Living, it will be halted because your
parents earn too much based on the job seeker's
income limit.
It's
one of those bills that possibly needs a lot more research done into it and
probably a much bigger-- To work with people
who have been in the sector with beneficiaries and that sort of thing to find
out what is a better situation to assess it, rather than
just put blanket arbitrary measures in or measures that
literally steer a particular outcome
that probably is the wrong outcome to be steered to.
If that makes sense.
I
believe that this should be halted or go back for a more thorough
consultation or have some serious amendments put in place to make sure that we
don't end up having the wrong decision made while
having the right decision wrongly withheld.
We're over time. Can I just ask you a quick question, Sam, though-
Go ahead
... before we go? Was there anything you found that helped
you get into employment?
From Work and Income, total waste of time.
I found they put up more barriers
to helping me
when I'd been on the unemployment benefit back then, than they
did to help me. Including one of them literally
scarred a job interview with
Trains Metro for the Wellington trains.
Work and Income screwed that up for me because they wanted a posted
letter of a job interview and wouldn't accept an email.
And
we're dealing with that type of scenario.
If I got that job there, I could be driving trains now.
But because one Work and Income case manager thought,
"Let's sit down there and put excessive road
barriers in the way," and I was 19 years old at the time when this happened, or
18. I can't remember. It was around about my 19th birthday.
Work and Income are too
strict as is. They don't do a good job of it.
I think a social worker would do a better job helping people find jobs.
I think a guidance counselor at school would do a better job at doing it.
The student union. There's a lot who could do a better job.
Work and Income just really don't get it right,
unfortunately.
All right. Well, thanks for coming and making a submission this afternoon, Sam.
Thank you. Thank you for having me.
Cheers.
Thank you.
All right.
I think we got Sylvie McCreen on now.
Sorry, Andrew Riddle.
Andrew Riddle?
Yes.
Okay, Andrew Riddle. Excellent.
He was next up, so he's in early.
Good on him.
Excellent.
Andrew Riddle.
Good evening, Andrew. Welcome.
Kia ora.
All right. We have you for five minutes. Thanks for coming in early.
We've had a few people drop off this afternoon, so we appreciate you
coming in early. The time is yours when you're ready.
Right. So I'll just start out with just a little bit of
what the situation is that we're in at the moment.
We've got, according to a report from the New Zealand Christian
Social
Services today,
roughly 473,000 people in
Aotearoa living in material hardship,
one in three people in food insecurity.
We have an undersupply of social and state housing,
which is at a level of about
half the percentage of
social and state housing as a percentage of the total housing stock of
countries that we regularly compare ourselves with.
And we currently have youth unemployment running at 16%.
We're also in a period now of real resource
underemployment. We are not a full employment
economy. We're clearly an economy that's in real resource
underemployment. The normal
behavior or the
effect of properly
organized and designed social security
support is that it acts as a
countercyclical
measure in times of such
underemployment. This bill is actually a
pro-cyclical measure. It'll make it worse.
It will be less money in circulation.
There'll be less money in circulation.
Now, that's just a standard Keynesian
analysis. It's bog standard stuff.
Anyway, as I make the point in my submission, the
whole premise behind the bill is based on a series of
economic myths,
which I explain in the submission.
And I just go on to say that the documentation behind this shows
that there was very little analysis and very little justification.
So, for example, the
income threshold for
18 and 19-year-olds not being
able to go onto unemployment
benefit is just above one person on the living wage.
And that's a household benefit. It's not that
much
higher than what a cabinet minister gets per annum as a housing allowance in
Wellington.
So I think that this bill is totally the wrong
approach, and a better approach is actually, instead of
punishing and being vindictive, is to actually be
positive and encourage and provide real
support for
unemployed youth
to go into training and
provide increased support. It is purely ridiculous to actually
suggest that unemployed youth can
go out and find work when we
have
the level of unemployment we have at the moment, and when we have the
16% youth unemployment. You're telling people to go out and find a job that
doesn't bloody exist.
Hmm.
I'm
sorry. I'm getting really angry just thinking about the cruelty of this
government and the cruelty of this bill.
It
doesn't very often, but it reduces me to tears thinking about it.
Can I ask a question?
All right.
Would it be all right if I ask a question?
Yeah.
Oh, wait. Let Andrew finish.
Are you finished?
I think that's enough. That's enough what I want.
We had an earlier submission from the NZCTU,
and they talked about practices overseas, which are
active employment practices, where you take someone, you
make sure that you're helping them find a job,
and most of those countries where that happens, that
person is financially supported while that happens.
Do you think that that might be particularly useful with
young people who aren't necessarily ready to go
into training, to get them into employment
rather than just simply cutting off the
support financially?
Yes, I do, and I note that that was also, I think, in the regulatory
impact statement, the preferred,
or sort of the preferred option of the officials.
Yes. We've heard, in fact, from quite a few submitters, that if you
have a job, it's often because of someone your family
knows giving you that job at that age.
So wouldn't that also help even out the playing field if people
who don't have those kinds of connections in their families were
able to succeed because of the help that the state gave them?
Isn't that the purpose of government?
Thank you.
And Andrew, I might just ask a question here because the advice that the government
has been given, which is, if you read the bill, you'll see it there.
Says that
18 and 19 year olds, on average,
are expected to be on a main benefit for 21 years if they
are on a benefit at 18 and 19 years old.
So you've focused just on the employment side of it, but this is employment
and training study as the other two components
of it.
So the expectation is to encourage young
people, these 18 and 19 year olds,
if they can't find employment, to study or to train, which will set them up for
a better life, I would posit, than being on a benefit for 21
years of their life. Would you agree in principle with that?
No. First thing is I would question the statistics you're
quoting
because I think it lacks nuance. The second thing is that
it's important to know
basically
what Helen White just
referred to. That sort of program is the sort of program you need,
not just throwing people on the rubbish heap and telling them
someone else is going to look after them, it's all on them, which is what this bill
is doing. The
statistics about 20, 21,
I think you've got to build in a whole lot of what is the support that was offered
when people were unemployed at 18 and 19,
and
just saying, "Oh, your family's earning just over the
living wage, your household, they can support you," is
not in any way a sensible,
caring measure.
All right. Well, thank you for sharing your perspective this afternoon, Andrew.
Thank you very much.
Sylvie coming.
Oh, yeah. Okay. We have Sylvie next.
Good evening, Sylvie.
Were you just on mute?
Oh, there we go. Check we can hear you.
Can you hear me?
Yes, we can. Excellent. Thank you. Five minutes is yours.
When you're ready, just fire away.
Tena koutou.
Ngā mihi to the tāngata whenua of this land.
Ngā iwi Māori katoa and those Māori whose ancestors
signed Te Tiriti o Waitangi and allowed me and my
ancestors to live and grow here as manuhiri in
relationship with them.
I'm here to Te Atiawa and Ngāti Toa, the people of the land
where the House you elected representatives sit.
Lest we forget that mana whenua graciously allow you to gather in
Poneke and make decisions that affect the wellbeing of their people
and the wellbeing of all who call Aotearoa home.
May those of us not linked to this land for hundreds of years
never forget that humble gratitude is a step we can take towards living the
promise of Te Tiriti o Waitangi.
My name is Sylvie McKenna.
I am Pākehā. I was born and raised in Poneke, though my
ancestors' bones lie in the earth of the British Isles.
I bring with me friends, whānau, comrades, community, ancestors, and
recently deceased loved ones.
These people have lit a fire in me for a just, fair, and caring
Aotearoa that honors Te Tiriti o Waitangi,
an Aotearoa that respects and cares for our most vulnerable
people,
an Aotearoa that learns from its mistakes and courageously leads
us and the rest of the world into a future that
wholeheartedly embraces indigenous leadership and
exemplifies honorable settler partnership.
I do not plan to be an expert on this bill.
I organized a group of friends and strangers to meet and write submissions
opposing the slew of attacks this current government aims to make on the
social and environmental fabric of our home.
I ticked the box that said oral submission, so here I am.
I've been given just over 24 hours notice to prepare for this oral submission.
I am angry and frightened by the haste
with which this government is moving through democratic processes
that are meant to ensure equitable participation in our
democracy.
Emphasis on the our.
May you remember who it is you serve,
the many and powerful,
not the few and rich.
I'm a post-graduate student of counseling and aim to one day counsel rangatahi
through secondary school and beyond
as they grow into adults.
It is my commitment to their future that brings me here today.
I see young people struggling under the pressures the government constructs
for them,
removing supports and changing the playing field all at the same time,
and in the middle of turbulent financial times where the shape of the workforce
changes day by day.
This proposed bill is yet another attack on rangatahi and whānau
to freely live and grow.
And the head to all the people and organizations that have spoken before me in
opposition to this bill.
My submission is in full support of their thorough research and on-the-ground
experience that helps them see the effects this policy would have on
rangatahi and whānau,
and the next step along the chain this policy would have on homelessness,
poverty, health,
and housing services,
and the justice system.
Thanks to the breadth of society represented by these
submissions.
Squeezing income support for young adults in the middle of a cost of living crisis
is cruel and heartless policy.
The assumption that parents are willing and able to fund their young adult children
living at home is laughably narrow-minded and
ignorant.
It is clear this bill has been thought up by the wealthy without any
consideration for the majority of families that are financially stretched.
The group of young people most exposed to the parental income test is also the
cohort most exposed to every other indicator of intergenerational poverty in
Aotearoa.
Rangatahi Māori,
Pacific young people, disabled young people, and young people in
low-income regional communities.
When will this government stop using beneficiaries as a punching bag?
We have extreme wealth in this country and more than enough to go
around.
Why take away what little there was from our most vulnerable
when our most wealthy swan around on super yachts, rape
Papatūānuku, and make bunkers to survive the climate apocalypse
they are responsible for?
All of us not in the super-rich bracket are struggling under increasing costs of
living and unemployment rates. Young people are challenged by these
circumstances and need support, not the rug pulled out from under them.
My recommendation is that the committee report the bill back to the House with a
recommendation that it not proceed. Do not pass go.
Kill the bill.
Fund beneficiaries and start making policy toward a universal basic
income so our society can flourish.
I want to live in a healthy, innovative, and inclusive Aotearoa,
and I know we all do, too. Thank you for your time.
Thanks, Sylvie, for coming and sharing your perspective this evening.
Thank you.
Thanks.
I've been advised all of the other submitters are no longer available,
so that concludes-
For the whole thing?
Yep.
Oh, my goodness. Oh, and Helen, you've just eaten all your snacks.